Hello everybody and welcome to WWDC 2012.
I'm very happy to be here and see you all here.
It's a big room.
So, I hope you like what you saw this morning
in the Keynote, there were lots of new announcements
lots of new hardware.
The new MacBook Pro,wow!
A great machine
We also announced a lot of new features in OSX
There was xxx new feature in OSX
And I'm not going to go through it again this afternoon
But a lot of new features in Mountain Lion, the new OSX
Same thing with iOS, a lot of new features
I think like 200 new features
And here again, I'm not going to go through all the features
Those are very great announcements
and I'm sure you're going to love those 2 OS's
So for you developers,
and I went through last time xxx one by one
And there were more than 3000 new APIs
I stopped at 3000
But there is like 3000 new APIs for you to discover
That is what this week is about
To dive into those new APIs
and learn, and see what you can use for your new product
Or when you update your current application
So with iOS and OSX, we have 2 huge ecosystems
Ecosystems built on top of the 2 leading platforms in the industry
At Apple, we care about the complete experience from end to end
So we care about the hardware, the software, the services
The content, and even the accessories
We want the user to experience the full experience from end to end
You developers are also part in this ecosystem
You're taking advantage of this huge ecosystem
to be able to sell your application to lots of customers
And so you are improving our ecosystem
and you are helping us to be so successful.
Some numbers were shown this morning
650,000 apps -- that's huge
I've been at Apple for more than 20 years
and believe me, this is huge
30 billion downloads -- that's also a humongous number
And 400 million Store Accounts
That's 400 million potential customers for your application
So a lot of customers
So, what you're going to do this afternoon
is step back a little bit
We want to give you 10 actual items
10 things that you should be doing in your next application
or when you upgrade your current application
10 things that we really care about
because we are spending a lot of resources,
a lot of time, a lot of effort on
And our customers want those things to be in your application
So we're going to go through those 10 action items
Take notes, there's going to be a quiz at the end
So let's start
Number 1: Design
So design is something we deeply care about here at Apple
In our hardware, in our software
Design is part of our DNA
We spend a lot of time designing our applications
designing our hardware
This is what we are all about
So for you developers, how does it start?
It starts with this big idea
"Oh my God, this big idea is going to be fantastic"
and -woof- you go and start typing code and writing code
And there is a big missing step here
You have to look at the design of your application
There is a famous quote that says
"Genius is 1% inspiration, and 99% perspiration"
For you, the idea is really the 1% here
The rest is how you're going to deliver
your idea to your customers
This is what's important
So, design -- what is this about?
We can define 3 types of design
There is the Interaction design
The Implementation design
and the Visual design
And they are not 3 steps that you can do 1, 2, 3 and you're done
and move on
They all -- this is something that's going to evolve during the lifetime
during your development cycle
And they are all interacting with each other
Your change in interaction design is going to change your implementation obviously, and it may change your visual.
So they are all working dependent on each other, and you have to constantly make them evolve.
Let's describe briefly what I mean here.
The interaction design is all about shaping your application for people use.
It means making it efficient, engaging, intuitive.
If you know the expression "Look and feel" - it's about the "feel" in "look and feel".
You don't want your user to have to read a 300 pages manual.
It's obvious, but ????????
We have great documentation at Apple with User Interface Guidelines - one for OS X and one for iOS.
Because the interaction is obviously not exactly the same.
So, read these documents. It's a most mandatory for you to read these documents.
Spend time understanding how you can implement the best interaction possible.
The single(?) type of design certain aspect of design is the implementation design.
And here I'm sure there are a lot of engineers in this room today. This is probably where you're gonna be spending most of your time.
This is about finding the right technology for your idea, the right architecture and the feature set.
Looking at performance, plan for your resources - the people, the time.
All those things that are key to be successful.
It's also the time to make the right trade-offs.
You may have this grandiose idea, but it turns out that, you know, the technology is not there, or you don't have time to do it so.
This is the time to figure out, what you can do in the time you have to go to market.
Finally, the visual design. This is about making your application beautiful and unique.
Giving the perfect experience to your customers.
This is about choosing the visual elements that are going to make your application unique.
The right typography, the right colour, the right patterns.
Everything that's going to make a memorable experience.
So, may sound obvious but you need to think about these things.
And figure out if you are going through this whole cycle for your application.
Skipping (?) on design - you wan't get what you want at the end.
You may have this great idea - but you wan't have any success.
So this is about design. Your first action item - don't skip on design.
The number two action item is about iCloud.
So iCloud is Apple cloud service. The idea is very simple.
We want our customer to have all their documents, all their stuff up in the cloud.
And they can access it wirelessly anywhere on any devices.
That's the goal of iCloud.
iCloud was introduced last year. It's integrated in OS X and iOS. It's a free service.
And it's simple and easy for our users to use.
As I said we are integrating iCloud in all our applications and services.
On iOS it is in Mail, Calendar, Address book. It's in Backup.
It's in the store, in the music store. We announced the new share photo stream.
It's in the iMessage. So we are including iCloud everywhere.
And on both iOS and OS X.
As of March of 2012 we had 125 Million iCloud users.