My name is Joshua Pennington
and I'm an engineer on the
Interface Builder Team
Today we're going to talk about
how you can adopt Storyboards
in your app.
We're going to cover a couple topics today.
We're going to start by giving
a quick overview of Storyboards.
Then my colleague Tony is going to
come up here and talk about
how you can adopt Storyboards in
applications that use code or xibs
And I'm going to finish by talking about
some great new features for Storyboards
in iOS 6.
Let's start with the basics.
This is a Storyboard.
This Storyboard allows to view you app's
entire user interface in one place.
And you can also view the transitions
between parts of your application
so you can very quickly get an overview
of the application just by glancing at it.
And there are two main concepts
in a Storyboard.
The first concept if that of a "scene".
A scene is a view controller, and it can
represent an entire screen in your app
or just one major component area, like a
split view pane
and a split view controller on iPad.
And you can drag in views, you can select
things and resize them.
You can inspect your attributes
in the inspector.
All of the normal interface builder
affordances are present here.
This is where you're gonna spend
most of your time fleshing out the UI
of your application.
So that's the first concept:
the scene.
The second concept if that
of a "segue".
A segue defines navigation in your
Storyboard.