Good morning.
My name is Brian Tucker, and I am a manager in the iOS software engineering group.
Primarily I'm responsible pretty much for all Bluetooth technologies on iOS platforms.
So this is Core Bluetooth 101, this is not basket weaving.
If you were looking for that, you're in the wrong room.
Core Bluetooth 101, primarily an API that focuses on Bluetooth Low Energy,
which is a new technology that was ratified by the Bluetooth Standards bodies.
I believe at the end of 2010. It was introduced in our products last year with iOS 5 and the iPhone 4S.
And - why do we think it's important to talk about this technology?
Well, I think that low energy - in the sense of low energy, if you look at the technology perspective -
really applies to every single person in this room as a consumer,
but especially as a technologist.
I'll give you an example:
I was in China earlier this year, and had the opportunity to speak on this topic in China
in front of about 2000 people.
And in China of course you have translators.
I had never spoken to a group of people with translators before.
They were sitting over there in this booth,
and they had picked somebody in the front row to tell me when to slow down.
Because when you speak fast, the translators are like machines
this stuff is just flying out of their mouth.
So you have this guy in the front who was flashing this flashlight at me
- he'd flash the flashlight when I was talking too fast.
I'm watching my timer and I know how many slides I have left
and I realize there's no way I'm going to get through these slides.
So I look at him and he looks at me and we have this showdown
and he realizes I'm not going to slow down.
So at any moment I'm pretty sure he's going to throw the flashlight at me.
But we get through it, get done on time
and all the slides got done
and I'm sure the translators are ready to shoot me.
So I walk down and I see the translators are running across the stage at me.
And I'm like here it is, I'm going to get killed.
Instead he comes up to me and says,
"That was amazing!"
And I'm like, "what?"
And he's like, "I've never talked that fast in my life!"
He said, "I'm gonna go home today and start working on this technology!"