Good Morning and Welcome to Session 714
For the next hour, myself and my
colleagues Conrad and Michael
are going to be talking about
protecting the user's data,
and the part that you, the developers,
can play in that.
First of all, a little bit about ourselves.
We are all members of the
platform security team at Apple
and we really operate up
and down the stack,
all the way down from
the secure bootloader,
all the way up to applications
and even the cloud.
But some times that we are always involved
is when a cryptographic key is used
to protect user's data.
That's technologies you've probably
come across before.
We also design and build solutions
for internal clients
For example, we were involved with
designing the cryptography
used by iMessage.
We expose a lot of that functionality,
through third part—
APIs for use by third parties
such as yourselves;
Security.framework, CommonCrypto
being examples.
That functionality is also exposed
by other Apple APIs at an even higher level,
for example, NSFileManager, CFNetwork,
and we're going to be pulling
from both of those layers
during this presentation.
What we're going to talk about:
We're going to look at a common situation,
which is a client app talking to
a web service.
We're going to subject it to
a hostile environment,
a simulated attack, and show what can happen,
talk about why that matters, and give some
simple steps that you can put
in your applications
to avoid falling foul of such attacks.