[ Silence ]
>> Hello, good afternoon,
welcome to session 505,
[ Silence ]
"Harnessing Metadata
in Audiovisual Media".
[ Silence ]
I've heard we are competing
with the "Intro to Swift" talk
[ Silence ]
so get intimate with
your neighbors here.
[ Silence ]
My name is Adam Sonnanstine.
I'm an engineer on
the AVFoundation team
[ Silence ]
and today we are going to talk
about, of course, metadata.
[ Silence ]
So what do I mean by metadata?
Well, for the purposes
of this talk we're going
[ Silence ]
to define metadata to mean
any data that is stored
[ Silence ]
in movie files, streaming
presentations, any other sort
[ Silence ]
of audiovisual presentation
that describes the primary data,
[ Silence ]
like the audio and video that
we think about when we think
[ Silence ]
of those sorts of presentations.
Some examples are
always helpful.
[ Silence ]
One you should be familiar
is iTunes metadata,
[ Silence ]
when you have this sort of
the song names and the artists
[ Silence ]
and the album artwork
in your iTunes library.
[ Silence ]
All these things are stored
as the sort of metadata
[ Silence ]
that I'm talking about
today in the files
[ Silence ]
in your iTunes library.
Besides iTunes metadata,
we also have things
[ Silence ]
like location information.
If you have a movie that
you took with your iPhone
[ Silence ]
or some other location-enabled
device and you played it
[ Silence ]
in QuickTime player, that will
show up in the info window
[ Silence ]
to tell you where you were
when you took that movie.
[ Silence ]
That's also stored as
the kind of metadata
[ Silence ]
that we are talking about today.
Some new features, we know that
you're not always standing still
[ Silence ]
when you are taking your videos.
So new in iOS 8 and OS X
Yosemite, we have features
[ Silence ]
that support things like dynamic
location, that's a location
[ Silence ]
that changes over time.
So these are some new features
that we are going to be talking
[ Silence ]
about later on that we are
pretty excited about and,
[ Silence ]
in addition to location, this
really applies to any sort
[ Silence ]
of metadata that you might
want to add that changes
[ Silence ]
over time in your movie.
This is a screen shot of a
demo app we'll show you later
[ Silence ]
but the circle and the
annotation text that's all
[ Silence ]
stored as the same sort of timed
metadata as a timed location.
[ Silence ]
So hopefully that whets
your appetite a little bit.
[ Silence ]
We'll talk about what
we're going to cover today,
[ Silence ]
we're going to start, I'm going
to give you an intro to metadata
[ Silence ]
and AVFoundation, some of
the classes that have been
[ Silence ]
around for a while for
describing all sorts
[ Silence ]
of metadata, how to inspect
that and how to author it.
[ Silence ]
We're going to talk more
about those new timed
metadata features
[ Silence ]
and then I'll give you some best
practices including some privacy
[ Silence ]
things to keep in mind and
some other best practices.
[ Silence ]
So our first topic: metadata
in AVFoundation..What kind
[ Silence ]
of classes are we going to be
using to describe our metadata?
[ Silence ]
Well our primary model
objects that we use
[ Silence ]
to describe both movie files
or HLS streams is AVAsset.
[ Silence ]
AVAsset can contain any
number of AV metadata objects
[ Silence ]
and each AVMetadataItem instance
represents a single piece
[ Silence ]
of metadata, either your
track name or your album mark,
[ Silence ]
even your location stuff that's
going to be separate pieces
[ Silence ]
of metadata in our
runtime environment.
[ Silence ]
So a closer look at
AVMetadataItem: at its core,
[ Silence ]
it has two properties.
The first is identifier, which
is actually a new property
[ Silence ]
and that is going
to describe the kind
[ Silence ]
of metadata that you have.
In this example we have the
song name and it's represented
[ Silence ]
by this long symbol name,
AVMetadataIdentifieriTunes
MetadataSongName,
[ Silence ]
and then you have the value
which is the actual payload
of the metadata item.
[ Silence ]
So for song name, it's the
name of the song as a string.
[ Silence ]
As an example for cover art,
you can see that the
value doesn't have
[ Silence ]
to be a string it can be an
image or any other object
[ Silence ]
that supports both the NSObject
and NSCopying protocols.
[ Silence ]
Now if you've used
AVMetadataItem
[ Silence ]
in the past you might
be familiar with the key
[ Silence ]
and key space properties.
Well the identifier I
mentioned that was new,
[ Silence ]
it's new because
it is a combination
[ Silence ]
of the old properties,
key and key space.
[ Silence ]
So I'm not going to talking much
about key and key space today
[ Silence ]
but mostly going to be talking
about identifier going forward
[ Silence ]
as the way to describe
your metadata.
[ Silence ]
Take a look at some of the
built-in identifiers we have;
[ Silence ]
this is just a tiny sampling.
There's a lot of them.
[ Silence ]
You can find them
in AVMetadataIdentifiers.h. I've
arranged them here according
[ Silence ]
roughly to the old notion of
key space so that's just sort
[ Silence ]
of a sampling of the kind of
metadata that we already know
[ Silence ]
that you might want
to represent.
[ Silence ]
Going back to the
metadata item itself,
[ Silence ]
we have a property that's
also new called dataType,
[ Silence ]
which describes the
native data type
[ Silence ]
that your metadata
is representing.
[ Silence ]
So for the case of our song
name it's stored as a string
[ Silence ]
so we see that the data
type is a UTF8 string;
[ Silence ]
and these string constants
that represent the different
data types are all defined
[ Silence ]
in CMMetadata.h. And besides
the data type property,
[ Silence ]
we also have several
type coercion properties
[ Silence ]
that you can use if you know
you want to get your payload
[ Silence ]
in the form of a certain
type of Objective C object.
[ Silence ]
So you have string value, number
value, date value and data value
[ Silence ]
and those are going to give
you exactly what you'd expect.
[ Silence ]
For the case of where our
native payload is a string,
[ Silence ]
only string value is going to
give you an interesting answer.
[ Silence ]
The rest will give you NULL.
For our artwork example where
the payload is a JPEG image,
[ Silence ]
the top three are
going to give you NULL
[ Silence ]
and the data value is going
to give you the NSData
[ Silence ]
that you're looking for to grab
the bytes of the JPEG image.
[ Silence ]
There are examples
where you can have more
[ Silence ]
than one non-nil
tech coercion method.
[ Silence ]
And one is creation date if
you have the date represented
[ Silence ]
as a standard string
format for dates.
[ Silence ]
You can either get the actual
string that was stored that way
[ Silence ]
or you can ask the metadata
item to give you an instance
[ Silence ]
of NSDate that describes
the same thing
[ Silence ]
in a more convenient
representation.
[ Silence ]
So that's your brief
intro to AVMetadataItem,
[ Silence ]
we're going to be talking a lot
about it throughout the talk.
[ Silence ]
Let's go back to AVAsset
so we can see how we actually
get these metadata items.
[ Silence ]
So the easiest way is just to
ask for all of the metadata
[ Silence ]
that applies to the
entire asset.
[ Silence ]
There are types of metadata that
apply to just parts of the asset
[ Silence ]
but this is how you get the
metadata to, like, the location
[ Silence ]
and the song title that
applies to the entire asset.
[ Silence ]
There's also a way to get
just a subset of the metadata.
[ Silence ]
We have this notion of metadata
format but I'm not going
[ Silence ]
to be talking about too much
today but you can use it
[ Silence ]
to get just that
subset of the metadata.
[ Silence ]
So for our example, when we
are getting iTunes metadata,
[ Silence ]
we're going to use that
AVMetadataFormatiTunesMetadata
[ Silence ]
and grab all of that using
the metadataForFormat method.
[ Silence ]
And then from there we can
use this filtering method,
[ Silence ]
metadataItemsFromArray,
filtered by an identifier
[ Silence ]
to get just the items
that correspond
[ Silence ]
to the song name identifier.
You might be wondering
why you can have more
[ Silence ]
than one song name
in a single asset?
[ Silence ]
We'll get back to that in just
a little bit but first I want
[ Silence ]
to talk about how you load the
payload of your metadata items.
[ Silence ]
AVMetadataItem conforms
to the
AVAsynchronousKeyValueLoading.h
[ Silence ]
protocol.
This is a protocol we define
ourselves in AVFoundation
[ Silence ]
and a lot of our core
model objects conform to it
[ Silence ]
because a lot of times
when you get an AVAsset
[ Silence ]
or an AVMetadataItem we haven't
actually loaded the data behind
[ Silence ]
it yet.
So you can use this method, load
values asynchronously for keys
[ Silence ]
to load the specific values
you want and they'll do
[ Silence ]
that asynchronously so you're
not blocking your main thread
[ Silence ]
with some sort of synchronous
I/O or something like that.
[ Silence ]
So for this case we
have our metadata item.
[ Silence ]
We're looking for the value so
we just load the key value and,
[ Silence ]
when we get our completion
handler,
[ Silence ]
we're going to check
the status to make sure
[ Silence ]
that that loading succeeded
and, assuming that we did,
[ Silence ]
we can then just go
ahead and grab the value
[ Silence ]
and use it however we see fit.
So back to that whole multiple
titles in one asset string.
[ Silence ]
Well, one reason we
might have that is
[ Silence ]
if we have the asset localized
in multiple languages.
[ Silence ]
So an asset can have
the same metadata items
[ Silence ]
in multiple languages.
The example that
we're going to talk
[ Silence ]
about is
QuickTimeUserDataFullName
[ Silence ]
dat identifier.
If you use this identifier
in your files,
[ Silence ]
then QuickTime Player, for
example, can pick up the title
[ Silence ]
and display it in the title bar.
So this is just yet
another example
[ Silence ]
of how metadata is used
in our applications.
[ Silence ]
This particular example
of the movie actually has the
title available in both English
[ Silence ]
and Spanish so here we have the
English as the system language
[ Silence ]
so QuickTime Player picks that
up, picks up the English title
[ Silence ]
but if we set our system
language to Spanish it will pick
[ Silence ]
up the Spanish localization
of that title instead.
[ Silence ]
These are represented as two
distinct pieces of metadata
[ Silence ]
within the file and the way that
you distinguish between them is
[ Silence ]
that they'll have
different values
[ Silence ]
for these final two properties
of AVMetadataItem locale
[ Silence ]
and extendedLanguageTag.
ExtendedLanguageTag is
new in this release.
[ Silence ]
It's a BCP 47 language tag
and it's particularly useful
[ Silence ]
when you want to
distinguish written languages.
[ Silence ]
So that's one reason
why you might have more
[ Silence ]
than one metadata item
with the same identifier.
[ Silence ]
So I mentioned before that
not all metadata applies
[ Silence ]
to the entire asset, well one
example of that is metadata
[ Silence ]
that only applies to
a particular track,
[ Silence ]
so for this example we have
a special label attached
[ Silence ]
to our subtitle track called
SDH, that stands for Subtitles
[ Silence ]
for the Deaf or Hard of Hearing
and that's basically just a
more rich form of subtitles
[ Silence ]
that includes things like
labeling who's talking
[ Silence ]
and mentioning sound effects
that are vital to
the understanding.
[ Silence ]
We talked a little bit more
about SDH and accessibility
[ Silence ]
in general last year in our
"Preparing and Presenting Media
[ Silence ]
for Accessibility" talk so check
that one out for more details.
[ Silence ]
For the purposes of this talk,
just know that to get
this SDH label here,
[ Silence ]
it involves setting
track-specific metadata.
[ Silence ]
So let's talk about
how you actually find
[ Silence ]
out if your track has
this metadata in it,
[ Silence ]
well you're going
to use AVAsset track
[ Silence ]
and it has pretty much
the exact same API
[ Silence ]
as AVAsset for reading metadata.
You have your metadata property;
[ Silence ]
you have your metadataForFormat
method and so if we want
[ Silence ]
to find all the tagged
characteristics that are
[ Silence ]
in an asset track, we're
going to ask the track
[ Silence ]
for its metadata for the
FormatQuickTimeUserData.
[ Silence ]
Once we have that we use
that same filtering method we
saw before in order to get all
[ Silence ]
of the items that
have the identifier,
[ Silence ]
QuickTimeUserDataTagged
Characteristic.
[ Silence ]
So this is one example of tagged
characteristics is the SDH
[ Silence ]
that I just talked about
and it's the payload
[ Silence ]
of the metadata items
that tells you what kind
[ Silence ]
of tagged characteristic
you're dealing with.
[ Silence ]
We'll talk a little bit
more detail about SDH
[ Silence ]
and how you author it
in just a little bit.
[ Silence ]
So going back to our list
of identifiers you might
have noticed some patterns
[ Silence ]
if you were looking closely.
Each of these groups has
their own version of a title
[ Silence ]
or a song name or
something like that.
[ Silence ]
We noticed that and come up
with our own special kind
[ Silence ]
of identifier called
a CommonIdentifier
[ Silence ]
which can be used when
you want to look up, say,
[ Silence ]
for this example a title without
caring exactly how it's stored
[ Silence ]
in your file.
Same for copyright here; we
also have a common identifier
[ Silence ]
that represents copyright.
These are not the only
common identifiers;
[ Silence ]
there's a whole list of them
but these are just two examples.
[ Silence ]
So if we go back to our
example where we're looking
[ Silence ]
for our iTunes song name,
if we don't actually care
[ Silence ]
that the title of our asset
is stored as iTunes metadata
[ Silence ]
and we just want a title so
we can display it somewhere,
[ Silence ]
you can ask the asset for
its array of commonMetadata
[ Silence ]
and this is all the
metadata items
[ Silence ]
that can be represented
using a common identifier.
[ Silence ]
Then you use that same filtering
method we've been using
[ Silence ]
to filter down to just the ones
that have the
CommonIdentifierTitle
[ Silence ]
and you can go from
there with your title.
[ Silence ]
Also worth noting is
that AVAssetTrack has the
same property, commonMetadata,
[ Silence ]
so you can do the same
thing over there as well.
[ Silence ]
So that is your brief
introduction
[ Silence ]
to inspecting metadata
with AVFoundation.
[ Silence ]
Let's talk a little
bit about authoring.
[ Silence ]
If you want to make your own
files that have say location
[ Silence ]
or iTunes metadata in them, we
have several different classes
[ Silence ]
that can write movie
files, AVAssetExportSession,
[ Silence ]
AVAssetWriter and the capture
movie and audio files outputs
[ Silence ]
and these all have the exact
same redirect property called
[ Silence ]
simply, metadata.
So you give an array of
metadata items and then
[ Silence ]
that will be written
out to the file.
[ Silence ]
Similarly for track-specific
metadata
[ Silence ]
like those tagged
characteristics,
[ Silence ]
you can use an AVAssetWriter
input
[ Silence ]
which also has the
exact same property.
[ Silence ]
Now you are not limited to
just writing out metadata
[ Silence ]
that you got from somewhere
else, like another file
[ Silence ]
through the APIs
we've been looking at.
[ Silence ]
You can also create
your own metadata items
[ Silence ]
with a mutable subclass
of metadataItem.
[ Silence ]
And as you might expect, this
just has read/write properties
[ Silence ]
for all of the properties
in AVMetadataItem.
[ Silence ]
So if we use an example of
writing a subtitle track
[ Silence ]
that is marked as SDH, well
it's actually two different tag
[ Silence ]
characteristics that
you have to use
[ Silence ]
and so we'll create two
different metadata items,
[ Silence ]
set both of their identifiers
to the identifier we just saw,
[ Silence ]
the QuickTimeUserData
tag characteristic,
[ Silence ]
but one of them will
set the value
[ Silence ]
to TranscribesSpokenDialogue
ForAccessibility
[ Silence ]
and the other will be
DescribesMusicAndSound
[ Silence ]
ForAccessibility.
Then we get the subtitle
AssetWriterInputthat's going
[ Silence ]
to write our subtitle track and
set that array of the two items
[ Silence ]
on our asset writer input.
So that's how you would
author a subtitle track
[ Silence ]
that is marked as SDH.
Just one example of
using tag characteristics
[ Silence ]
in AVMutableMetadataItem.
Special note about
AVAssetExportSession:
[ Silence ]
by default the ExportSession
is actually going to take any
[ Silence ]
of the metadata that's
in the source asset
[ Silence ]
that you're exporting.
It's going to copy that
over to the output file.
[ Silence ]
Now that's not the case
if you set metadata
[ Silence ]
on its metadata property.
That will be the signal
to tell the ExportSession
[ Silence ]
to ignore the metadata
in the source file
[ Silence ]
and instead write just what
you put on the property.
[ Silence ]
So if you want to do
augmentation of the metadata
[ Silence ]
or some other sort of
modification you'll want to grab
[ Silence ]
that array of metadata,
make a mutable copy
[ Silence ]
and do any adjustments
that you want and then set
[ Silence ]
that on the metadata property.
So that's just a quick
note about ExportSession.
[ Silence ]
The last note about authoring
metadata is HTTP Live Streaming,
[ Silence ]
this is actually a new
feature in iOS 8, OS X Yosemite
[ Silence ]
and you can use a new tag
called session-data tag
[ Silence ]
in your playlist, which
has two required fields:
[ Silence ]
the data ID which is a
lot like our identifiers
[ Silence ]
that we're talking about, a URI
which can point to the payload
[ Silence ]
or a value which directly
specifies the payload and,
[ Silence ]
optionally, some
language information.
[ Silence ]
So here's an example
that shows very similar
[ Silence ]
to what we saw before
with the titles
[ Silence ]
in two different languages but
this is the markup you'd use
[ Silence ]
for HTTP Live Streaming.
So for more information
on reading
[ Silence ]
and writing metadata we
do have some sample code,
[ Silence ]
it's called AVmetadataeditor
and for more information
[ Silence ]
about the details of writing
HTTP Live Streaming metadata see
[ Silence ]
the documents at this URL.
All right so that is your
crash course in metadata
[ Silence ]
in AVFoundation, our next
topic is timed metadata.
[ Silence ]
So timed metadata, although I
mentioned we have new features,
[ Silence ]
it is not a new concept.
We supported the notion of
chapters for quite some time
[ Silence ]
and conceptually chapters
are just an example
[ Silence ]
of times metadata.
Each of these chapter markers
is just a piece of metadata
[ Silence ]
that is describing
a particular range
[ Silence ]
of the timeline of the movie.
That's all that timed
metadata is,
[ Silence ]
it's just metadata associated
with a range of time.
[ Silence ]
So similarly, with our
dynamic location example,
[ Silence ]
we have the path that's drawn
here that's really just composed
[ Silence ]
of a number of pieces
of metadata indicating
the current location,
[ Silence ]
each one of them associated
with a particular time
[ Silence ]
in the movie's timeline.
So to demonstrate
QuickTime Player's features
[ Silence ]
with dynamic location
in Yosemite,
[ Silence ]
I want to bring my
colleague, Shalini,
[ Silence ]
up to the stage for a demo.
>> Hi, I'm here to
demonstrate how to read
[ Silence ]
and play back metadata
using QuickTime Player.
[ Silence ]
Here I have a movie file
which has both audio and video
[ Silence ]
and timed locations data
stored in a different track.
[ Silence ]
So now if I bring this
up in QuickTime Player,
[ Silence ]
this is the usual UI
for audio and video.
[ Silence ]
New in OS X Yosemite:
in the Movie Inspector
you can see a map view
[ Silence ]
if your movie file
has location data.
[ Silence ]
Your map view is presented
along with the route
[ Silence ]
where you have recorded
this video.
[ Silence ]
So here the blue line
indicates the path
[ Silence ]
where we recorded the video and
the red pin is an indication
[ Silence ]
of the current location
or the location
[ Silence ]
on the timeline of the movie.
So if I zoom in a little
bit and start play,
[ Silence ]
you can see as the movie
progresses the pin's location is
[ Silence ]
being updated to be in
sync with the video.
[ Silence ]
I can drag the scrubber around
and you can see the pin
moving back and forth.
[ Silence ]
I can also go and click
at any point in the map
[ Silence ]
and you see the video seek
to that location to present
[ Silence ]
where your video was when
you were at that location.
[ Silence ]
This is map view in QuickTime
Player on OS X Yosemite.
[ Silence ]
>> Thank you, Shalini.
So let's talk about
what we just saw there.
[ Silence ]
So that location information
was stored as timed metadata
[ Silence ]
in the file and in order to
have QuickTime Player draw
[ Silence ]
that information on the map, we
use AVAssetReader to read all
[ Silence ]
of the location information
from that asset.
[ Silence ]
And because timed metadata
is stored in its own track,
[ Silence ]
we use an
AVAssetReaderTrackOutput to read
[ Silence ]
that data and we use a new
class called AVAssetReaderOutput
[ Silence ]
MetadataAdaptor that knows how
to give us that data in the
[ Silence ]
from of a class called
AVTimedMetadataGroup.
[ Silence ]
Then from there we
can grab each location
[ Silence ]
and draw that path on the map.
So AVTimedMetadataGroup
is a very simple class.
[ Silence ]
It's really just
these two properties:
[ Silence ]
an array of metadata items
combined with a time range
[ Silence ]
that describes where in the
movie that data applies.
[ Silence ]
So to see a little bit of
code for using AssetReader
[ Silence ]
for this purpose, the
first thing you want
[ Silence ]
to do is find the track
that contains your location
information and we'll talk more
[ Silence ]
about how to do that
in just a second.
[ Silence ]
Then you use that track to
create an AssetReaderTrackOutput
[ Silence ]
and you use nil output settings
and then you'll create
your metadataAdaptor
[ Silence ]
with that trackOutput.
And then, in a loop we just
take your metadataAdaptor
[ Silence ]
and call the
nextTimedMetadataGroup method
[ Silence ]
over and over again, doing
something with each piece
[ Silence ]
of data, like drawing
it on the map
[ Silence ]
until that method returns nil.
Then you know there's
no more data to draw.
[ Silence ]
So in terms of finding
the right track to read,
[ Silence ]
the way you're going to do
that is by examining the tracks
[ Silence ]
in your asset and looking
through the format description
[ Silence ]
of each track to find the
identifiers you're looking for.
[ Silence ]
So you first start
by getting the tracks
[ Silence ]
with the MediaTypeMetadata
and then for each
[ Silence ]
of those tracks you're
going to loop through all
[ Silence ]
of its format descriptions,
usually there's only one
[ Silence ]
and for each format description
you're going to grab its list
[ Silence ]
of identifiers using this
function and check whether
[ Silence ]
that identifier array
contains the identifier you're
[ Silence ]
looking for.
In this case we're looking
[ Silence ]
for the location
ISO 6709 identifier.
[ Silence ]
So once we've found it we're
good to go and we can resume
[ Silence ]
with the code on
the previous slide.
[ Silence ]
So that's how QuickTime
Player is drawing the map
[ Silence ]
or drawing the path on the
map before you start playback.
[ Silence ]
The other thing that QuickTime
Player does, as you saw,
[ Silence ]
is it can update the current
location while you're doing
[ Silence ]
playback or even scrubbing
around and the way it does
[ Silence ]
that while it's already playing
the asset using an AVPlayerItem
[ Silence ]
and we're going to
use a new class called
[ Silence ]
AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput that
you attach to your PlayerItem,
[ Silence ]
which also notes how to
vend this data in the form
[ Silence ]
of TimedMetadataGroups.
But unlike the asset reader,
instead of getting all the data
[ Silence ]
up front you're going
to be getting it piece
[ Silence ]
by piece as the movie plays.
So a little bit of code,
[ Silence ]
you first create your
metadata output using the
[ Silence ]
initWithIdentifiers method
and in this case we're only
interested in metadata that has
[ Silence ]
that location identifier so
that's all we're going to get
[ Silence ]
by opting into this way.
Then you create a
delegate that you define
[ Silence ]
and that's what's going
to receive the metadata
during playback and you set
[ Silence ]
that delegate on your output
and tell us what cue you
want us to send the data on.
[ Silence ]
Then you create or grab your
AVPlayerItem and call addOutput
[ Silence ]
to attach your output, to attach
your output to the playerItem
[ Silence ]
and finally make your player
and associate your item
[ Silence ]
with the player as the current
item and start playback.
[ Silence ]
It's important to get the
smoothest playback experience
[ Silence ]
possible, we highly recommend
that you do all of this sort
[ Silence ]
of setup work before
you start playback
[ Silence ]
or even attach the
item to the player.
[ Silence ]
So a little bit of look at
what your delegate method might
[ Silence ]
look like.
There's only one delegate
method; it's the metadataOutput,
[ Silence ]
didOutputTimedMetadataGroups,
fromPlayerItemTrack method.
[ Silence ]
And the first thing you
want to do is grab an item
[ Silence ]
that you can get your
payload data from.
[ Silence ]
In this case, to
keep things simple,
[ Silence ]
I'm just grabbing the first item
from the first group but keep
[ Silence ]
in mind there could
be multiple items,
[ Silence ]
there could even
be multiple groups.
[ Silence ]
One reason there could
be multiple groups given
[ Silence ]
to this method is that the
metadata output will keep track
[ Silence ]
of whether the metadata
is coming faster
[ Silence ]
than you're processing it and,
if it is, it will start to batch
[ Silence ]
that up and give you
the metadata in batches
[ Silence ]
when you're done with the
previous batch of metadata.
[ Silence ]
So moving on with your
item; you're going
[ Silence ]
to do this
LoadValueAsynchronouslyForKeys
[ Silence ]
dance that we talked
about before.
[ Silence ]
In this case, we're
interested in the value
[ Silence ]
and data type properties
so we're going
[ Silence ]
to load both of those.
I've admitted the error
checking for brevity here
[ Silence ]
which you'll probably want
to do that error checking
[ Silence ]
like we had in the other slide.
And once we have the completion
handler we can ask the item
[ Silence ]
for its data type and make
sure that's the data type we're
[ Silence ]
prepared to handle, in this
case my code only knows how
[ Silence ]
to handle location information
in ISO 6709 format so we got
[ Silence ]
to make sure that's the right
data type and from there we go
[ Silence ]
and dispatch our code
to the main thread
[ Silence ]
that will update our UI.
So that's how QuickTime Player
is updating the location
[ Silence ]
metadata during playback.
Of course this is not the
first API that we have offered
[ Silence ]
for reading timed
metadata during playback.
[ Silence ]
There is an existing
property called timedMetadata
[ Silence ]
on AVPlayerItem but
I'm here to say
[ Silence ]
that the
AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput
[ Silence ]
replaces that property for
all of these use cases.
[ Silence ]
Now we're not deprecating
the property yet
[ Silence ]
but we do recommend, if
you're new to timed metadata,
[ Silence ]
just adopt the metadataOutput
and not worry about
the property.
[ Silence ]
If you're already using the
property version we do recommend
[ Silence ]
that you move over but just you
know that you should make sure
[ Silence ]
that your code is working
properly after that transition,
[ Silence ]
in particular I'll point
out that the metadataOutput
will give you, for certain kinds
[ Silence ]
of HLS content, will give
more specific identifiers
[ Silence ]
than the old property did.
So just make sure your code
is prepared to handle that.
[ Silence ]
The last topic on reading
timed metadata is Chapters.
[ Silence ]
Chapters, like I said, have
been supported for some time;
[ Silence ]
they even have their own API:
chapterMetadataGroupsBest
MatchingPreferredLanguages.
[ Silence ]
This is on AVAsset.
This will give you an array
of timed metadata groups
[ Silence ]
that contain items
with the identifier,
[ Silence ]
QuickTimeUserDataChapter,
and we've supported this
[ Silence ]
for some time for QuickTime
movie files and M4Vs and,
[ Silence ]
new in iOS 8 is the-and OS X
Yosemite-is support for chapters
[ Silence ]
in HTTP Live Streams
as well as MP3 files.
[ Silence ]
And I'll tell you more about how
to author those HLS chapters
in just a little bit.
[ Silence ]
So for more information,
we have some sample code
[ Silence ]
that does approximately what
QuickTime Player is doing,
[ Silence ]
where it can show your
location during play back.
[ Silence ]
We also have a previous session
about AssetReader that goes
[ Silence ]
into much more detail than I did
here, called "Working with Media
[ Silence ]
in AVFoundation" from 2011.
So that's how you read and
play back timed metadata.
[ Silence ]
Our next timed metadata topic
is how you can create your own
[ Silence ]
movies that contain
timed metadata.
[ Silence ]
We saw the screenshot
before and I mentioned
[ Silence ]
that these annotations are
stored as timed metadata and,
[ Silence ]
to show you this demo app, I'd
like to invite Shalini back
[ Silence ]
up on stage to demo it.
>> This time let's
look at an app on how
[ Silence ]
to author your own custom
metadata movie files.
[ Silence ]
Here I have a video and if I
would like to share some notes
[ Silence ]
with my friend, who is good
at fixing colors in a movie,
[ Silence ]
I can now do that
within the app.
[ Silence ]
To add annotations, I
use a two-finger gesture,
[ Silence ]
I can use a pinch gesture to
resize and then add a comment
[ Silence ]
which is enough for my whoever
looks at the video later
[ Silence ]
to fix the colors there
and then I begin playback.
[ Silence ]
And as playback progresses,
I track the circle
[ Silence ]
to where I want this
to be fixed.
[ Silence ]
And now that I have this
annotation and I can write it
[ Silence ]
out along with the audio and
video to do that, I hit "export"
[ Silence ]
and now we see an AV
player view controller
[ Silence ]
which shows the exported
movie along with the metadata
[ Silence ]
which was written to it.
So if I start playback you see
the annotation is moving along
[ Silence ]
the timeline in the
part in which I traced.
[ Silence ]
So if I scrub back in time you
can see the annotation moving.
[ Silence ]
You might wonder that
the annotation is baked
[ Silence ]
into the video frame; it is not.
It is being rendered real-time
using AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput
[ Silence ]
and you can change the color
or the font of the annotation.
[ Silence ]
So if I begin playback, you
see the rendering is happening
[ Silence ]
in real time.
That's AVTimedAnnotationWriter,
we have this available
[ Silence ]
as a sample code
as well, thank you.
[ Silence ]
>> So that was a
great demonstration
[ Silence ]
of not only the playback part
of it but also how to write
[ Silence ]
that data into the file,
so let's take a look at how
[ Silence ]
that was accomplished.
So we're going to use an
AVAssetWriter to write the file
[ Silence ]
and we're going to use an
AVAssetWriterInput in order
[ Silence ]
to write that metadata
track to the file.
[ Silence ]
Just like the reader side,
the writer has a new class
that's a metadataAdaptor
[ Silence ]
and that class knows how
to interpret instances
[ Silence ]
of AVTimedMetadataGroup and
write that into the file.
[ Silence ]
See a little bit of code;
first thing we're going
[ Silence ]
to do is create our
AssetWriter Input.
[ Silence ]
We're going to use the media
type AVMediaTypeMetadata,
[ Silence ]
once again nil outputSettings
and we're going to have
[ Silence ]
to provide a clue to
the source format, well,
[ Silence ]
the format of the data that
we're going to be appending.
[ Silence ]
We'll talk more about this
and why it's required
on the next slide.
[ Silence ]
Then you simply create
your metadataAdaptor
[ Silence ]
with the reference to that
input and, as you generate
[ Silence ]
or receive your timed
metadata groups,
[ Silence ]
you simply use the
appendTimedMetadataGroup method
[ Silence ]
to continue to append those
and write them to the file.
[ Silence ]
So what's the deal with
that source format thing.
[ Silence ]
Well, it turns out in order
for AVAssetWriter to be able
[ Silence ]
to write your metadata in the
most efficient way possible,
[ Silence ]
it needs to know up
front exactly what kind
[ Silence ]
of metadata it is
going to be writing.
[ Silence ]
This will result in the most
lowest storage overhead in terms
[ Silence ]
of the number of bytes
your file takes up
[ Silence ]
and it also has a effect
on how efficient it is
[ Silence ]
to play back this
kind of contents.
[ Silence ]
You don't want to be
using too much power
[ Silence ]
when you're playing this
kind of content back.
[ Silence ]
So you do have some
options in terms
[ Silence ]
of how you actually construct
one of these format hits.
[ Silence ]
If you're reading
from AVAssetReader you
can actually ask the track
[ Silence ]
that you are reading
from to give you its list
[ Silence ]
of format descriptions
and use one of those.
[ Silence ]
If you're creating the metadata
group yourself or getting it
[ Silence ]
from some other source then
you can use a new method called
[ Silence ]
copyFormatDescription that
will give you back an instance
[ Silence ]
of CM format description that
will do this job for you.
[ Silence ]
It's important to note that
if you go this route you need
[ Silence ]
to make sure that the contents
of your metadata group
are comprehensive in terms
[ Silence ]
of it containing
every combination
[ Silence ]
of identifier data
type and language tag
[ Silence ]
that you are going
to be appending.
[ Silence ]
That is, it contains an item
with each of those combinations.
[ Silence ]
Of course, since the CM format
description is a CF type,
[ Silence ]
you'll need a CFRelease
app when you're done.
[ Silence ]
Of course, there's one
more way you can do this:
[ Silence ]
you can create the format
description directly using
[ Silence ]
CoreMedia APIs.
And here you use this long name
CMMetadataFormatDescription
[ Silence ]
CreateWith
MetadataSpecifications function.
[ Silence ]
You're going to pass in
the metadataType box.
[ Silence ]
That's the sort of
metadata we've been talking
[ Silence ]
about this whole time
with timed metadata.
[ Silence ]
And these metadata
specifications it's just an
[ Silence ]
array of dictionaries.
Each dictionary contains those
combinations I was talking
[ Silence ]
about before.
The identifier dataType and
optionally extended language tag
[ Silence ]
so you want to make one of
these metadata specifications
[ Silence ]
dictionaries for each
combination you plan to append.
[ Silence ]
So the one thing that was not
obvious about that demo is
[ Silence ]
that we're actually writing
metadata timed metadata
[ Silence ]
that describes one
particular other track.
[ Silence ]
So for the example
of these annotations,
[ Silence ]
we're really just talking about
the video track of the movie
[ Silence ]
and not the sound or
anything else like that.
[ Silence ]
So just like we had a way of
making track-specific metadata
[ Silence ]
that applied to the
entire track,
[ Silence ]
with those tagged
characteristics
[ Silence ]
that we saw before, you
also have the ability
[ Silence ]
to formerly mark
your metadata track
[ Silence ]
as describing one
particular other track.
[ Silence ]
You do that with the
addTrackAssociationWith
[ Silence ]
TrackOfInput method using as the
parameter the AssetWriterInput
[ Silence ]
that you are using to
write your video track.
[ Silence ]
And your receiver is the
input that you are using
[ Silence ]
to write your metadata track.
You use the
AssociationTypeMetadataReferent.
[ Silence ]
So that's how your create
metadata that's timed
[ Silence ]
but also specific to
a particular track.
[ Silence ]
The next thing we did that was
interesting in that demo is
[ Silence ]
that we actually used our
own custom identifiers.
[ Silence ]
So we had that big list
of built in identifiers.
[ Silence ]
Well, you don't have
to use those;
[ Silence ]
you can actually build your own
and as I mentioned before an
identifier is just a combination
[ Silence ]
of key space and key and
it has a particular format:
[ Silence ]
it's just a string but it
is in a particular format
[ Silence ]
so to help you make your
own custom identifiers,
[ Silence ]
we have this method,
identifierFor Key, and keySpace,
[ Silence ]
it's a class method
on AVMetadataItem.
[ Silence ]
There are some rules to
follow: your key space needs
[ Silence ]
to be four characters
long if you want to use it
[ Silence ]
for timed metadata
so we actually recommend you
use our built-in key space,
[ Silence ]
the QuickTimeMetadata keySpace.
We also highly recommend
you use reverse DNS notation
[ Silence ]
for your custom keys
to avoid collisions
[ Silence ]
with other kinds of metadata.
So a brief code snippet you
can see you can simply use this
[ Silence ]
method to make your custom
identifier and then set
[ Silence ]
that on the identifier property
of your mutableMetadataItem.
[ Silence ]
So in addition to custom
identifiers you can also create
[ Silence ]
your own custom data types.
So we're all familiar by now,
through this presentation,
[ Silence ]
with some of the built-in
data types that we defined;
[ Silence ]
there's a lot more than these
but we've been using these
quite heavily already.
[ Silence ]
These are really useful
but sometimes you want
your data type information
[ Silence ]
to express more, maybe about
the domain you're working in,
[ Silence ]
so if you are doing a serial
number or a bar code kind
[ Silence ]
of thing you might want
to define a data type that's
this sort of serial number
[ Silence ]
as string data type or
barcode image as JPEG data type
[ Silence ]
so you have more
specific information
[ Silence ]
about what your metadata
actually contains.
[ Silence ]
The way that this works is,
you have to tell us exactly how
[ Silence ]
to serialize that custom
data type and the way you do
[ Silence ]
that is you tell us that your
custom data type conforms to one
[ Silence ]
of our built-in data types.
So in this case the
serial number conforms
[ Silence ]
to the UTF8 data type so under
the hood it's UTF8 string,
[ Silence ]
but we know that it really
represents a serial number
[ Silence ]
and the same with
the barcode image.
[ Silence ]
The way that you do this is you
register your data type using
[ Silence ]
the CMMetadataDataTypeRegistry
RegisterDataType function that's
[ Silence ]
defined in Core Media.
You can't create your
own custom base types
[ Silence ]
but you can create your own
custom type that conforms
[ Silence ]
to our raw data built-in type
if your data type really is
just a custom sequence of bytes.
[ Silence ]
So there are some rules
to using AVAssetWriter
[ Silence ]
for writing timed metadata.
Most importantly, every metadata
item that you append has
[ Silence ]
to have non-nil values for
identifier, data type and value.
[ Silence ]
Your identifier has to conform
to the format that we specify,
[ Silence ]
so we highly recommend
using that utility method
[ Silence ]
that we just talked about.
The value has to be
compatible with the data type
[ Silence ]
so you can tell us that your
NSString value is an UTF8 string
[ Silence ]
but don't try telling us
that your custom class is a UTF8
string because we won't know how
[ Silence ]
to serialize that properly
and the AssetWriter will fail.
[ Silence ]
As I mentioned before, you have
to create your AssetWriterInput
[ Silence ]
with a format hint and
that must be comprehensive
[ Silence ]
and we described that before.
So the last topic
about AssetWriter
[ Silence ]
and timed metadata is a recipe
for creating your own movies
[ Silence ]
that have the same sort
of dynamic location
[ Silence ]
that we've seen a
couple of times already.
[ Silence ]
To do this, you can
use AVCapture audio
[ Silence ]
and video data outputs
and target that data
[ Silence ]
at twin instances of
AssetWriterInput and,
[ Silence ]
at the same time, grab
information from Core Location
[ Silence ]
that represents the location
information and write
[ Silence ]
that to its own
AssetWriterInput.
[ Silence ]
For more detail about how to do
that we've actually implemented
[ Silence ]
that and made it
available as sample code,
[ Silence ]
so see AVCaptureLocation if you
want to make your own movies
[ Silence ]
that contain dynamic location.
We also have sample code
as Shalini mentioned
[ Silence ]
for the demo we just showed you,
that's called
AVTimedAnnotationWriter.
[ Silence ]
And, of course, for more
information about AssetWriter
[ Silence ]
in general, see that same
talk I referenced earlier:
[ Silence ]
"Working with Media
in AVFoundation".
[ Silence ]
Last two quick topics about
timed metadata: ExportSession.
[ Silence ]
Just like we've said the
asset ExportSession will
[ Silence ]
by default pass through any
of your metadata that applies
[ Silence ]
to the entire asset or
entire track, it will pass
[ Silence ]
that through, copy it
to the output file.
[ Silence ]
It will do the same thing with
timed metadata that exists
[ Silence ]
in the source file provided
that your destination file
type is QuickTime Movie.
[ Silence ]
We'll talk more about file
types in just a little bit
[ Silence ]
but basically ExportSession
behaves exactly
[ Silence ]
as you would expect.
In our last timed metadata
authoring topic is HTTP Live
[ Silence ]
Streaming chapters so if
you want to author chapters
[ Silence ]
in your HLS stream, you can use
the session-data tag we talked
[ Silence ]
about earlier and the special
data ID, com.apple.hls.chapters.
[ Silence ]
Your URL should point
to a JSON file
[ Silence ]
that describes the chapter
information for that stream and,
[ Silence ]
of course for more detail
on this, see that same link
[ Silence ]
that I referenced earlier
for HTTP Live Streaming.
[ Silence ]
All right, so that
is timed metadata,
[ Silence ]
our next topic is privacy.
Why is privacy important
in this context?
[ Silence ]
Well, any time that you
are writing your users data
[ Silence ]
to a file you need to
be at least considerate
[ Silence ]
about their privacy and be aware
that the metadata that you write
[ Silence ]
out to these movie files can
contain user identifiable
[ Silence ]
information, the most obvious
example of that is location.
[ Silence ]
And so because movie files
can be distributed and we want
[ Silence ]
to protect the privacy
of our users,
[ Silence ]
for our built-in sharing
services, we do our best
[ Silence ]
to strip out any potentially
user identifiable information,
[ Silence ]
such as this location and we
recommend that you do the same.
[ Silence ]
So we've given you a utility
for that called
AVMetadataItemFilter.
[ Silence ]
Right now there is only one
filter that we make available
[ Silence ]
but it is geared
towards privacy,
[ Silence ]
it is the metadata item filter
for sharing and that will strip
[ Silence ]
out any of this sort of
user identifying information
[ Silence ]
that we're talking about;
location is only one example.
[ Silence ]
But it will also strip out
anything it doesn't recognize,
[ Silence ]
because it doesn't know whether
that might contain user
identifiable information.
[ Silence ]
So that includes any
metadata that uses identifiers
[ Silence ]
that you define yourself.
It will leave in some things
like metadata that's important
[ Silence ]
to the structure of the movie
and chapters are the
best example of that,
[ Silence ]
and also any commercial
related data like your Apple ID.
[ Silence ]
So to use the MetadataItemFilter
you're going to first
[ Silence ]
of all create your filter and
feed it your original array
[ Silence ]
of metadata items using
this metadataItemsFromArray
[ Silence ]
filteredByMetadataItemFilter
method.
[ Silence ]
This is a companion to that
other filtering method based
[ Silence ]
on identifiers we've
been using all day
[ Silence ]
and then once you have
your filtered array
[ Silence ]
of metadata items just set
that on your AssetWriter
[ Silence ]
or ExportSession as
you normally would.
[ Silence ]
Well actually I mentioned
ExportSession
[ Silence ]
but things can be simple if
you're using the ExportSession
[ Silence ]
and only want to
copy the metadata
[ Silence ]
from the source asset
and not add your own.
[ Silence ]
You just set the filter
on the ExportSession
[ Silence ]
and it will actually do
the filtering for you,
[ Silence ]
this will filter both
static and timed metadata
[ Silence ]
but it will only filter the
metadata from the source asset.
[ Silence ]
If you set your own metadata
on the metadata property,
[ Silence ]
it won't filter that for you;
you'll need to do the process
[ Silence ]
that I just described of
doing the filtering yourself.
[ Silence ]
The only other thing
to keep in mind is
[ Silence ]
that the export may
take more time
[ Silence ]
when the filter is being used
because it has to go through
[ Silence ]
and examine all of
the metadata items.
[ Silence ]
So that's privacy.
Our last section of the talk
today is some assorted best
[ Silence ]
practices when you are
writing your own files
[ Silence ]
that contain metadata.
First up, what if you're
writing timed metadata
[ Silence ]
and you have multiple
streams of metadata
[ Silence ]
that use different identifiers.
How do you get those
into the same file?
[ Silence ]
Well, we actually have the
situation in the demo app,
[ Silence ]
we have that circle is comprised
of two different pieces
[ Silence ]
of information, the
position and the radius.
[ Silence ]
So we're representing these
and the demo app is two
distinct streams of metadata.
[ Silence ]
And so the most obvious way
I can think of to get this
[ Silence ]
into a file is to use two
different AVAssetWriterInputs,
[ Silence ]
which result in having
two metadata tracks
[ Silence ]
in the output file,
pretty simple.
[ Silence ]
But there is another
way you can do it,
[ Silence ]
you could instead combine those
two different types of metadata
[ Silence ]
into one timed metadata
group and write
[ Silence ]
that to a single
AssetWriterInput
[ Silence ]
and that will result in
only one metadata track
[ Silence ]
in the output file that contains
multiple different kinds
[ Silence ]
of identifiers.
There are some advantages to
this approach, not the least
[ Silence ]
of which is it can result
in lower storage overhead
[ Silence ]
and therefore as we always
see more efficient playback.
[ Silence ]
But there are of course
pros and cons to everything.
[ Silence ]
So you'll definitely want
to consider combining
[ Silence ]
into one track your
different metadata
[ Silence ]
if they are used
together during playback
[ Silence ]
and they have identical timing.
This is definitely the case
with the example we just saw
[ Silence ]
with the circle center
and the circle radius.
[ Silence ]
If these are not true then
you might not want to combine.
[ Silence ]
And in fact one instance where
you definitely do not want
[ Silence ]
to combine, is if
you have one type
[ Silence ]
of metadata that's associated
with another track in the file,
[ Silence ]
so that's like our
annotations are associated
[ Silence ]
with the video track, but
then you have another type
[ Silence ]
of metadata like location
that is associated
[ Silence ]
with the entire asset.
You don't want to combine
those into one track,
[ Silence ]
otherwise your location in that
example will become mistakenly
[ Silence ]
associated with just
the video track,
[ Silence ]
and that's not what you want.
So that's how to deal
[ Silence ]
with multiple streams
of timed metadata.
[ Silence ]
Next topic is duration of
your timed metadata groups,
[ Silence ]
when you get a timed
metadata group
[ Silence ]
from AVFoundation
it's always going
[ Silence ]
to have a fully formed
time range.
[ Silence ]
So that means it will have
a start time and a duration.
[ Silence ]
We actually recommend when you
make your own timed metadata
[ Silence ]
groups for a pending
with the AVAssetWriter
[ Silence ]
that you don't bother
giving us a duration.
[ Silence ]
And to see how that works,
here's an example of a group
[ Silence ]
that starts at time 0 but
it doesn't have a duration
[ Silence ]
so how do we know when it ends?
Well, of course we'll wait
until you append the next one
[ Silence ]
and then we'll say that,
"Okay, the end time
[ Silence ]
of the first group is the same
as the start time
of the next one."
[ Silence ]
So this ensures that your
metadata track is going
[ Silence ]
to have a continuous stream of
contiguous metadata and we think
[ Silence ]
that for most cases this is the
best way to store your metadata.
[ Silence ]
The way you accomplish this is,
when you're making
your time range,
[ Silence ]
you just use KCMTimeInvalid
for your duration
[ Silence ]
and we'll take care of the rest.
We do recognize that there are
cases where you might not want
[ Silence ]
to have contiguous
metadata, you might want
[ Silence ]
to author an explicit gap into
your metadata stream and so,
[ Silence ]
for that, our recommendation
is that you give us
[ Silence ]
in the middle there a group
that contains zero items.
[ Silence ]
This is the best way to
author a gap in the metadata.
[ Silence ]
And you can see we just do that
by presenting an empty array
[ Silence ]
when we're creating our
timed metadata group.
[ Silence ]
Notice that we're still
using KCMTimeInvalid
[ Silence ]
for our duration here.
Just tell us when the beginning
of the metadata silence,
[ Silence ]
so to speak, is and we'll figure
out how long it lasts based
[ Silence ]
on when you append your
next non-empty group.
[ Silence ]
So that's how you write
gaps in your metadata.
[ Silence ]
Our last best practice,
I mentioned output
file type before
[ Silence ]
and here's the longer
explanation.
[ Silence ]
Well, AssetWriter
and AssetExportSessions
support writing
[ Silence ]
to a wide variety of file types.
You've got QuickTime
movie, MPEG4, and all sorts
[ Silence ]
of other kind of file types
and those file types can carry
different kinds of metadata;
[ Silence ]
some have more restrictions
than others about what kind
[ Silence ]
of metadata can go
into that file type.
[ Silence ]
So the easiest situation, say
if you have an ExportSession
[ Silence ]
and you're going from one,
from the same file type
[ Silence ]
as your source to the output,
so for this example they're
both QuickTime movie files.
[ Silence ]
This is the easiest
way to ensure that all
[ Silence ]
of that data is actually going
to make it into the output file.
[ Silence ]
If instead you're using a
different output file type,
[ Silence ]
like MPEG4 in this example,
then some different things
are going to have to happen.
[ Silence ]
You notice those last few
items didn't quite make it
[ Silence ]
into the output file;
it's because they have no
equivalent representation
[ Silence ]
that works with an MPEG4 file.
If you're looking
closely you'll also notice
[ Silence ]
that those top two
items have changed,
[ Silence ]
although they sound very similar
they are slightly different
[ Silence ]
identifiers because that's
the kind of identifier
[ Silence ]
that works with MPEG4.
So both AssetExportSession and
AssetWriter will do the sort
[ Silence ]
of three step process.
First, they'll try to pass
that data through directly
[ Silence ]
if possible and, if not, they'll
try to convert the identifier
[ Silence ]
into an equivalent
representation
[ Silence ]
in the output file type.
If neither of those work, we
have no choice but to just drop
[ Silence ]
that piece of metadata
on the floor.
[ Silence ]
So in terms of guidance on how
to choose an output file type,
[ Silence ]
well, my two recommendations
are,
[ Silence ]
if you are using say an
ExportSession to copy all
[ Silence ]
of the metadata, timed or
otherwise, from the source asset
[ Silence ]
to your destination file,
the best way is to try
[ Silence ]
and use the same file type
that you started with,
[ Silence ]
and if you don't know what the
file type is you can use the
[ Silence ]
NSURLTypeIdentifierKey
to find out.
[ Silence ]
You can also always use
the QuickTime Movie file
[ Silence ]
because that is going to
have the greatest chance
[ Silence ]
of supporting your metadata
no matter where it came from.
[ Silence ]
If AVFoundation supports
it, there's a good chance
[ Silence ]
that it will be supported
by the QuickTime movie file.
[ Silence ]
Of course, this is the only way
if you're writing
timed metadata,
[ Silence ]
to get your timed
metadata into a file is
[ Silence ]
to use QuickTime Movie file;
it's the only file form
[ Silence ]
that supports it right now.
Of course good advice is always
[ Silence ]
to check the results,
no matter what.
[ Silence ]
Check that your output files
contain the kind of metadata
[ Silence ]
that you expect, all the
metadata that you expect
[ Silence ]
and you can choose to
use some of the APIs
[ Silence ]
that we've already
talked about if you want
[ Silence ]
to do that at runtime.
Some guidance if that
doesn't end up being the case:
[ Silence ]
if you don't get all the
metadata that you expect, well,
[ Silence ]
you can try to do the
conversion yourself.
[ Silence ]
Especially if you have a
custom identifier and are going
[ Silence ]
to a file type that doesn't
support your custom identifier,
[ Silence ]
take a look at that long list
of built-in identifiers we have
[ Silence ]
and see if there is something
that's roughly equivalent
[ Silence ]
to what you're trying
to store and you can do
[ Silence ]
that conversion yourself.
One particular example
I want to call
[ Silence ]
out that involves only
built-in identifiers is
[ Silence ]
when you're trying to
go from ID3 to iTunes,
[ Silence ]
well AVFoundation
currently isn't going to do
[ Silence ]
that conversion for you.
But there's no reason you
couldn't do that yourself,
[ Silence ]
so once again just take a look
at our long list of identifiers
[ Silence ]
and match them up and do the
conversion in your own code.
[ Silence ]
So that is the end of the talk.
See what we covered: we talked
obviously a lot about metadata
[ Silence ]
in AVFoundation,
we talked about all
[ Silence ]
of the different classes
you can use for inspection,
[ Silence ]
we talked about AVAsset
and AVMetadataItem
[ Silence ]
and how those work
together and also authoring,
[ Silence ]
we talked about the AssetWriter,
the AssetExportSession even
briefly on the capture audio
[ Silence ]
and movie file outputs.
We dove into timed metadata,
including all the new features
[ Silence ]
that enable things like
the dynamic location
[ Silence ]
and your own timed metadata
like the annotation demo.
[ Silence ]
We also talked about
privacy considerations
[ Silence ]
and some best practices like how
to choose the right file type.
[ Silence ]
So for more information, you
can contact our evangelism team
[ Silence ]
or see our programing guide,
there are some other
related sessions you might be
[ Silence ]
interested in.
If you missed this
morning's presentation
[ Silence ]
on "Modern Media
Playback", you can catch
[ Silence ]
that on the video recording.
Tomorrow there is also a
camera capture talk focusing
[ Silence ]
on manual controls.
And on Thursday we'll have
a talk about direct access
[ Silence ]
to video encoding and
decoding, which I'm sure a lot
[ Silence ]
of you will be interested in.